Finding Aid for Lynwood Beekman papers, 1966-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lynwood Beekman papers
1966-2007
1977-1998
Beekman, Lynwood.
2011041 Aa 2
Collection of correspondence, records of committees and organizations, legislation drafts, and research material on the subject of Special Education programs and services, created and used by Lynwood Beekman in his law practice and in drafting of the Michigan Special Education legislation.
9.25 linear feet in 10 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Lynwood Beekman (donor no. 10479 ) in December 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Lynwood Beekman is a Lansing, Mich. native and the University of Michigan Law School graduate. Beekman's father, Marvin E. Beekman, was Director of Special Education for Lansing Public Schools. He established the nation's first public school work experience program for the mentally disabled. Later, as the State's Director of Special Education, Marvin E. Beekman guided Michigan to a leadership position in service to the mentally impaired.
Lynwood Beekman's 30-year law career has been largely devoted to the representation of parents and their children with disabilities, over 90 Michigan school districts, and the Michigan Education Association and its members, including teachers, school psychologists, school social workers, bus drivers, paraprofessionals, etc. Beekman served in over 600 matters as a hearing officer and state review officer in three states. He has provided consultative assistance or hearing officer and mediator trainings for 46 states and the Bureau of Indian Affairs. He has also served as a mediator, neutral evaluator, arbitrator, and complaint investigator in over 300 cases, including several matters pending before state and federal courts. He provided counsel to the Michigan Association for Retarded Citizens (ARC), and sought special education programs and services for many impaired residents of State institutions. Beekman collaborated in drafting the Mandatory Special Education Act and revised Special Education Rules, among other important pieces of Special Education legislation. In 1975 Beekman founded the Citizens Alliance to Uphold Special Education and served as its President for 13 years. In 1976 he was appointed by the State Superintendent of Public Instruction to the Special Education Task Force that was primarily drafting of the new or revised Special Education Rules. For six years Beekman served as the Chairperson of the State Board of Education's Special Education Advisory Committee. Beekman also served as Chairperson of the State Board of Education's Special Education Delivery System Task Force.
The collection documents the work of Lynwood Beekman and legislative history of Special Education in Michigan. The papers are arranged in five series roughly following Beekman's original arrangement of papers and records. The collection consists primarily of records of the Department of Education and its committees and task forces, as well as Special Education organizations. Also included numerous drafts of legislation, generously peppered with Beekman's scrupulous handwritten notes, and working files.
Subjects:
Beekman, Lynwood.; Beekman, Marvin E.; Michigan. Dept. of Education.; Special education--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Special education--Michigan--History.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Mandatory Special Education and Life Services
  The Mandatory Special Education and Life Services series contains records of task forces and organizations that worked on drafting and revising the Mandatory Special Education Act. Records include correspondence and memoranda, questionnaires, recommendations and reports, minutes of meetings, drafts, discussion points and responses, report reviews and analysis.
  - Mandatory Special Education Act
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1969-1974; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Working files and drafts, 1966-1971; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Regulations, 1969-1974; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Task Force on Special Education
    - Correspondence and memoranda, general, 1976-1978; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Delivery System Subcommittee, [, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Finance Subcommittee, 1977; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Legislative Subcommittee
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
      - Mandatory Special Education Act, 1977 (Box 1)
      - Special Education Code, 1977; 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Report, June 12, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Perceptions of the Field Subcommittee, 1977 (Box 1)
    - State Leadership Subcommittee, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Mandatory Special Education Report, July 1977; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Public hearings, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Task Force recommendations reviews, 1977-1978; 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Implementation of plan, 1978-1981; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Gene Ceasar, educational consultant papers, 1971-1978 (Box 2)
  - Parent Advisory Committee
    - Records
      - 1975-1977 (Box 2)
      - 1980-1986, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Workshop, September 1980 (Box 2)
    - Publications, 1980 undated (Box 2)
  - Special Education Delivery System Task Force
    - Intermediate School District Plan for Delivery of Special Education and Services (ISD Plan), 1980-1992 (scattered) (Box 3)
    - Concerns, 1991-1993 (Box 3)
    - Rosters, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Steering Committee, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
    - Subcommittees, 1993-1994; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1993-1995; 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Report correspondence and memoranda, 1993-1995 (Box 3)
    - Report draft, undated (Box 3)
    - Preliminary report, April-May 1994; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Final report, July 1994 (Box 3)
    - Responses to report, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Analysis report, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Speeches, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Mandatory Life Services
    - Michigan Association for Retarded Citizens (MARC) (Box 4)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 4)
      - 1983-1986, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Model Life Services Project, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Matrix, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Project to Assure Services for Handicapped Citizens (PASH), 1984-1987 (Box 4)
    - Five-Year State Plan for Independent Living Programs and Services in the state of Michigan (State Independent Living Council, 1992 ) (Box 4)
- Michigan Department of Education
  The Michigan Department of Education series contains material related to MDE's legislative work in the area of Special Education, namely administrative rules, procedures related to hearings and hearing officers training, non-compliance and disputes, and regulations, and records of several MDE committees and workgroups on special education. Records include correspondence and memoranda, texts and discussion of proposals and legislation drafts and final versions.
  - Legislation
    - Special Education State Plan
      - 1971 (Box 4)
      - 1980-1985 (Box 4)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 4)
      - 1991 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1973-1981; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1994-1999; 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Michigan Dept. of Management and Budget, 1991; 1996-1997 (Box 4)
    - Legislation drafts (Box 4)
    - School Code
      - 1976-1977 (Box 4)
      - 1997-1999, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 2001 (Box 4)
    - Administrative Rules for Special Education, 1997-1999; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Special Education Code proposal responses, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
    - Demised proposals, 1977-1980; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (IDEA) Implementation Agreement, 1997-1998 (Box 5)
    - Preliminary rules, 1980-1981; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Permanent Emergency Rules, 1981-1982; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Special Education Rules revision, 1984; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Runkel Rules, 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Runkel Rules, 1986; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Proposed rules, 2001 (Box 6)
  - Committees and workgroups
    - Inclusive Education Committee, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
    - School Health Issues workgroup, 1990-1999 (scattered) (Box 6)
    - Medications in School workgroup, 1996-1997 (Box 6)
  - Procedures
    - Hearings
      - 1974-1981, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1983-1989 (scattered) (Box 6)
      - 1992-2001, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Hearings, 2002-2006; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Non-Compliance scattered, 1970s-1980s (Box 7)
    - Disputes
      - 1990-1991 (Box 7)
      - 1994-1996 (Box 7)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 7)
      - 2006-2007 (Box 7)
    - Process statute, 1999-2002; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Continuous Improvement Monitoring Process (CIMP), 1991-2002 (scattered) (Box 7)
- Special Education organizations and cases
  The Special Education Organizations and Cases series contains records of several Michigan organizations advocating Special Education in Michigan and, and materials of court cases. The series contains records of Michigan Association for Retarded Citizens (MARC), Special Education Service Area (SESA), and Special Education Advisory Committee (SEAC). Included here are correspondence and memoranda, policies, and court materials.
  - Michigan Association for Retarded Citizens (MARC)
    - Documents and correspondence (Box 7)
    - 1972-1977, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Court documents, 1974-1975; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Agreements, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Special Education Service Area (SESA)
    - Leadership, 1975-1978; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Proposals, 1975-1977 (Box 8)
    - Response letters, 1975-1979; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Special Education Advisory Committee (SEAC)
    - Ad Hoc Rules Committee
      - 1979-1982 (Box 8)
      - 1984-1985, 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Policy Committee, 1981; 1984-1987 (Box 8)
    - SEAC expansion, 1979-1983; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Michigan Department of Social Services (DSS)
    - Beekman et al v DSS
      - Pleadings, 1987-1991; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Court of Appeals, 1991-1992 (Box 8)
      - Supreme Court, 1994-1995 (Box 8)
      - Working files and research, 1986-1994 (scattered) (Box 8)
- Working Files
  The Working Files series contains materials on various topics used by Lynwood Beekman throughout his career. Material is organized in approximate chronological order. Files include correspondence, memoranda, articles, notes, statistical data, etc. Also included are two audiotapes of the State Board of Education meeting of April 18, 1979, with partial transcription.
  - History of Special Education in Michigan, 1970s-1980s (scattered) (Box 9)
  - Future of Special Education Committee, 1991-1992 (Box 9)
  - State Schools
    - 1974 (Box 9)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 9)
  - Private Schools, 1985-1989 (scattered); 2005 (Box 9)
  - Mental Health v Special Education, 1980 (Box 9)
  - Special Education Cost Cutting, 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Caseloads, 1981-1987 (scattered) (Box 9)
  - Medically fragile children, 1983; 1990-1992 (Box 9)
  - Study of Transportation of Medically Fragile Children, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Medication and physical therapy in schools, 1983; 1987; 1996 (Box 9)
  - Corporal punishment, 1984; 1987; 1991 (Box 9)
  - Weightedness, 1989; 1993 (Box 9)
  - Special Education speeches, 1983-1984; undated (Box 9)
  - Legislative action talks, 1995-1998; 2001 (Box 9)
  - State level hearings, 1995-1998; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Committee on Lovaas/Style Interventions, 1995-1996 (Box 9)
  - Special Education legislation meeting, 2002; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1971; 1980; 1996 (Box 9)
  - State Board of Education meeting, April 18, 1979; 2 audiocassettes with partial transcription (Box 9)
  - Printed materials
    - Special Education Curriculum Guide, 1971 (Box 10)
    - Guidelines for Special Education Programs and Services in Michigan (Michigan Department of Education), 1974 (Box 10)
    - Guidelines for Special Education Programs and Services in Michigan Rev. ed. (Michigan Department of Education), 1977 (Box 10)
    - Alternatives to Litigation: The Necessity for Parent Consultation, [1977] (Box 10)
    - State Board of Education Recommendations for Legislative Action, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Special Education Rules (Michigan State Board of Education), 1980; 1982-1983 (Box 10)
    - Request for Proposal, Fiscal Year 1980/1981 (State of Michigan Developmental Disabilities Program, Michigan Department of Mental Health) (Box 10)
    - The Michigan School Aid Act [of 1979] Compiled and Appendices, 1998 (Box 10)
- Marvin E. Beekman
  The Marvin E. Beekman series contains papers and photographs of Lynwood Beekman's father. Included in the series are materials on the subject of history of special education in Lansing, Mich. and miscellaneous items. Photographs in the series depict Marvin E. Beekman's retirement event.
  - History of Special Education in Lansing, Mich, 1955-1967 (scattered) (Box 10)
  - Basic Driver Education by Bouner, Gutshall, and Kenel (Lansing, Mich.: Special Education Pub.), 1966 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970s-1990s (scattered) (Box 10)
  - Photographs, 1972-1973 (Box 10)